Bissell family collection
Litchfield Historical Society
Bissell family collection
1760-1926
Litchfield Historical Society 7 South Street, P.O. Box 385 Litchfield, CT, 6759 URL: http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org/archon Email: archivist@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org Phone: 860-567-4501 Fax: 860-567-3565
Bissell, William, 1810-1902; Bissell, Warren, 1836-1913
4.00
The papers of the Bissell and Bissell-Baldwin families, including family members, friends, and business associates. The collection consists of correspondence, business records, account books, and other records. Papers from the time period 1760-1840 have been processed and described (see the finding aid). The remaining papers have been partially processed and are described generally in this scope and content note.
1949-24-0
Biographical Note
William Bissell (1810-1902) of Litchfield was a captain in the Civil War, a house painter, and a farmer. He served in Company A, 19th Regiment Connecticut Volunteers from Sep. 11, 1861 to July 21, 1863. Subsequent to active duty he recruited in the Litchfield area.
Scope and Contents
The papers of the Bissell and Bissell-Baldwin families, including family members, friends, and business associates. The collection consists of correspondence, business records, account books, and other records. Papers from the time period 1760-1840 have been processed and described (see the finding aid). The remaining papers have been partially processed and are described generally in this scope and content note.
Isaac Bissell (1682-1744) moved to Litchfield in 1723, where he owned a 60th share, approximately 700 acres. He was the father of ten children, including Benjamin (1717-1747) and Zebulon (1724-1777).
The Bissells were farmers, although there is little material in the Society's manuscript collections that records their agricultural activities. Assorted Bissell family members are parties to documents found in various collections. As a family of property, most of the available documents document land transactions.
The Bissell Family Collection, received from several sources, brings together documents of many Bissell family members. In bulk, the business papers of William Bissell (1810-1902) and his son Warren (1836-1913) comprise the greater portion. They resided in Milton. William owned the David Welch house from 1860 to 1902. This significant house of 18th century construction is listed in "Historic American Building Survey" (1941) and is the subject of Edward A. Raymond's pamphlet, "History of the David Welch House, 1756-1956."
The activities of William Bissell as a captain in the Civil War, as an industrious house painter, and as a farmer are documented. He served in Company A, 19th Regiment Connecticut Volunteers from Sep. 11, 1861 to July 21, 1863. Subsequent to active duty he recruited in the Litchfield area. The papers include recruitment records with names and bounty accounts and supply and inventory documents for his term of active duty. His activities as a house and furniture painter are detailed in 33 small account books (1825-1890) in which his labor and supply costs for each specific job site are recorded. Another account book provides additional information.
A facet of Warren Bissell's economic interests are revealed in a collection of business letters and documents (1906-1926) pertaining to speculative investments in western mines and land companies. Other business documents include bills and receipts for paint supplies, wall paper, and transportation. Other papers include property deeds.
A small collection of deeds and letters relate to the members of the family of Zebulon Bissell (1724-1771). One subject is a family misunderstanding concerning the lease of a farm in Chanango County, N.Y. to a nephew Harry Smith.
The Bissell-Baldwin Collection of 11 items relates to the family of Julia Bissell Smith who was a great great grandmother of donor George Baldwin. A letter by Julia Smith from Tuscumbria, Ala., June 6, 1836, describes to her mother the thoroughly unfamiliar southern way of life.
The Baldwin descendants Margaret, Dorothy, and George, all donors to the Society, are related to the Bissell and Joseph Adams families. Ella Kezia Adams, who married Charles Baldwin, was the daughter of Charles Adams and the granddaughter of Joseph Adams. See also the Adams Family Collection.
Arrangement of Materials
Papers from the time period 1760-1840 have been processed and described. The remaining papers have been partially processed.
Related Materials
Adams family collection, Litchfield Historical Society
Separated Materials
Series 1: Items 1,2,3 - John Bissell Military Commissions - are currently stored in aisle 18B Box 2. (Oversize)
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Baldwin family; Bissell family
Genre/Form of Material:
Account books; Business records; Correspondence; Deeds; Drawings; Military records
Geographic Name:
Litchfield (Conn.); United States -- Social life and customs
Topical Term:
Bissell, Zebulon, 1724-1771; House painting; Mineral industries; Smith, Julia Bissell; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Litchfield Historical Society from Henry Swanson on 01/01/1949.
Accruals
Henry Swanson gave a trunk containing papers of William Bissell in 1949 (1949-36-0) which comprises the bulk of the collection. Additional smaller gifts came from Mrs. Jerome Bissell in 1942 (1942-03-0), Mrs. Chudleigh Hicks in 1954 (1954-04-0) and 1966 (1966-06-0), Mrs. Philip Plumb in 1955 (1955-34-0), Mrs. Stanley Coe in 1959 (1959-01-0), Mr. and Mrs. James Doyle (1965-24-0), and found in collection (2010-109-0).
Other Information
This collection was processed with support from the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR) and the National Historical Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Bissell papers, 1760-1839
  - Bissell, Bejamin to Smith, Harry, 1833, 1835 (Folder 1)
    - 1833 Mar 20 (Folder 1)
      Writes concerning deed.
    - 1835 Jan 7 (Folder 1)
      Prospects for selling wool, furs, etc. No further knowledge of Smith's father's estate. News of family and friends.
  - Bissell, Erastus to Smith, Augustus, 1836 Aug 23 (Folder 2)
    Family news, does not wish to enter the tanning business without his cousin, severe winter in Litchfield, some relatives have gone to Alabama.
  - Bissell, Nathaniel to Smith, Rebecca Bissell, 1839 Nov 15 (Folder 3)
    Suggests to Rebecca that she and her son Harry make an amicable arrangement concerning the farm.
  - Cookbook, Bissell, Harriet, 1832 (Folder 4)
  - Deed, Grant, Josiah to Bissell, Benjamin and Bissell, Leah, 1745 Nov 28 (Folder 5)
  - Deed, Ellery, John to Bissell, Zebulon, 1760 Apr 21 (Folder 6)
  - Deed, Colver, Asher to Bissell, Zebulon, 1760 Sep 6 (Folder 7)
  - Deed, Bissell, Joseph to Webster, Justus, 1769 Nov 14 (Folder 8)
  - Deed, Pettibone, Samuel to Bissell, Zebulon; Smith, John; and Parmalee, Amos, 1775 Apr 4 (Folder 9)
  - Deed, Bissell, Zebulon to Bissell, Benjamin, 1780 Jan 17 (Folder 10)
  - Deed, Bissell, Zebulon; Landon, John; Landon, Abigail Bissell; Blakeslee, Arunah; and Blakeslee, Rhoda Bissell to Bissell, Benjamin, 1781 Sep 26 (Folder 11)
  - Deed, Beebe, Bezaleel to Bissell, Benjamin, 1788 Apr 12 (Folder 12)
  - Deed, Thomas, Joseph to Bissell, Benjamin, 1812 Oct 19 (Folder 13)
  - Deed, Bissell, John and Bissell, Caty Marsh to Seymour Ozias, 1817 May 28 (Folder 14)
  - Deed, Bissell, Benjamin to Smith, Harry, 1840 Jan 13 (Folder 15)
  - Hoadley[?], Silas to Bissell, William, 1833 Aug 30 (Folder 16)
    Payment of a debt.
  - Land survey, Bissell, George, 1793 Nov 20 (Folder 17)
  - Last will and testament, Bissell, Benjamin, 1824 Jul 3 (Folder 18)
  - Quit claim deed, Bissell, Abigail Smith to Bissell, Benjamin, 1778 Apr 9 (Folder 19)
  - Writing book, Bissell, William, 1833 (Folder 20)
  - Military commission, New York, Bissell, Capt. John, 1835
    Currently stored in 18B box 2.
  - Military commission, New York, Bissell, Capt. John, 1836
  - Military commission, New York, Bissell, John, Judge advocate, 1837
- Bissell-Baldwin papers, 1785-1839
  - Bissell, Amos to Smith, Julia Bissell, 1827 Mar 9 (Folder 1)
    News about Dr. Beecher leaving and the new preacher, Mr. Stone, and of friends and acquaintances.
  - Bissell, Amos to Smith, Julia Bissell, 1827 Mar 9 (Folder 2)
    Announces his intention to marry L.
  - Bissell, Lydia Hall to Smith, Julia Bissell, 1828 Feb 18 (Folder 3)
    Announces arrival of a son and news of family and friends.
  - Deed, Bissell, Benjamin to Cranston, James, 1810 Aug 30 (Folder 4)
  - Osborn, Alemda to Smith, Julia Bissell, 1820 Oct 28 (Folder 5)
    Primarily religious in nature, also describes her difficulties as a teacher.
  - Smith, Julia Bissell to Bissell, Esther Benton, 1826 Jun 7 (Folder 6)
    Describes her trip to Solebury, Pa., the Quakers, and her new home with her husband and daughter.
  - Smith, Julia Bissell to Bissell, Eunice, 1829 May 10 (Folder 7)
    Describes her husband's religious conversion and her hopes for the same for her brother and his wife.
  - Smith, Julia Bissell to Esther Benton Bissell, 1836 Jun 6 (Folder 8)
    Writing from Tuscumbria, Ala., she writes about slavery, the southern life, and her husband's store.
  - Smith, Julia Bissell and Smith, Lyman to Bissell, Esther Benton, 1839 Nov 4 (Folder 9)
    Writing from Mount Carmel, Ill., she writes about family news, her joining a church, activities of the children, discussion of Mr. Smith's plans and possible relocation.
  - Turril, Joel to Benton, Eunice, 1785 Sep 20 (Folder 10)
    A love letter.